let's move now on copy-on-write so if you
remember I mentioned when we were
discussing processes and fork that it might
look strange when we want to create a new
process to actually create a copy of the
process that is currently running using fork
but that in practice there are very efficient
ways to do this and now we are going to
have a look at what I meant now that we
know what paging and virtual memory is
so copy-on-write is an example of the benefits
you can gain when you decouple what is the logical
representation of memory from the physical one
so when you create a copy of a process and you're
using the copy and write mechanism then the
new process the copy of the original process
does not really need to load in memory its own
let's say set of instructions and data since
they are the same of the initial process but it
can actually share the same space in memory that
belongs to the original process of course as long
as it's only reading that and it's not modifying
that since we have a page table we can initially
set the address of each page to be actually in the
frame that belongs to the other process if we are
only going to read those pages then it's perfectly
fine actually in fact all the pages that are there
only to be read and not written we can keep using
the ones of the original process what we need to
do is that whenever one of the two processes tries
to modify a page since now these modifications
do not need to be observed by both the
the parent and the child not only they don't
need they should not be observed by both
then in that case we can throw a page fault and
load again the page but a copy of it for the
process that wants to modify it and you have
variations of fork that you can use actually
to use the copy-on-write mechanism so it
looks like this if process two is created by forking
process one each one will have its own page table
in a different portion of memory but the content
of the page table so the addresses of the
frames can be the same for the two of them okay we
have three pages here so they are both pointing to
the same page that's why creating a process
to fork it's extremely fast because in fact
you don't really need to load anything into memory
you just have to create of course a new page table
the process control block of the new process
but when it comes to the information that
belongs to the process in memory
you can just keep using the one of the
parent process if process one let's say wants
to modify a certain page c then in that
case you create a copy of it this is just
a slide that put here since a couple of years
to give you an indication that of course what
we discuss in this course it's not only basics
of computer science but it's also something
that is active an active field of research
here you have an example that comes from security
so I'm not going into details here but turns out
that there was a bug in the implementation
of the copy and write mechanism and that
could be exploited to gain access to parts of
memory that should not have been granted access
and this thing was there the bug since 2007
and you see that it was like nine year more
than nine years after that it was discovered and
this was four years ago so it's just to give an
indication that these things we are discussing
right now it's they are also part of research